hi everybody let's get straight into it
a basic kit would have a mat and
hopefully a needle in some sort of
container to keep it nice and safe
here's the needles they come in their
numbers 36 38 gauge the lower the number
the bigger it is this is a triangular
shaped needle and the little notches on
it of Barb's and the barbs are what help
map the wall together the needles are
extremely sharp so do be careful with
them so that's your needle you should
get and also in your kicked hopefully
you'll get some oh if you're lucky
you'll get an extra tool holder it makes
it easier to have a handle on the
needles sometimes this one comes apart
and you can put several needles in it
which can speed up your work and also
you might get finger protectors is it
great so one goes on your first finger
and one goes on your thumb most of the
time now I don't use them because I feel
unhappy and I like to be able to feel
the world but when you start this is
what you're going to have no way so this
is your will hopefully you'll get some
will in the starter kit this is a carded
wool now if you hold it and pull it like
that it won't come apart if you hold it
gently
it eases apart so there's certain ways
to handle the world if you are more
gentle as you pull it will work better
so take a bit of well put your finger
protectors on and roll what we're doing
the first sheet we're doing is a ball we
are actually going to make something
don't think just because you're a
beginner you can't make anything it is
so easy needle felting so roll it up
into a sort of ball shape now take your
needle and start putting your needle
into the world here's a close-up so as
you go into the will come out in the
same direction and in the same angle do
not put your needle in and twist it
alternate go in and out in the same
angle if you do twist or turn this can
lead to the needle breaking so you will
find that you will break a few needles
is completely normal
don't worry but as a starter you've got
to get the feel a bit and see how it
goes
so take the ball and just keep putting
the needle in and out in and out this
ball will probably in all take about
five minutes to do but once you get the
hang of it it's something you can do
easily all the time it's it's it's such
a fantastic thing to learn needle
buzzing so a lot of people oh this is
what happens if you do break a needle
see there's the ball is quite a firm
ball the needle snaps and this n bit is
left in
your fealty project you have to get that
end it out so that's what it will look
like if it rains so a lot of people say
support is needle felting what is it all
about well originally years ago there's
two types of needles there's two types
of felting there's wet felting and dry
felting so wet felting is obviously
exactly as indicate to use water you can
make these balls wet felting but I think
they take about two days to dry so I
would rather do something instantly it's
much nicer
need I have to worry about it drying but
wet felting was how it originally
started in Italy to make bags and shoes
and routes and things that had a sort of
a material type feel to it so I'm just
showing you starting to form together a
little bit so with dry felting you can
do lots of sculpting you can make
animals peep and flowers very stuffs all
3d but you can do anything you want to
do which is why I love it
but what happens is the needle goes in
and the barbs Matt or knit the fibers
together and they knock it in
so if you'll need all that from
something it would they'll only get
smaller and firmer
you can openly talk about things and
make them really really firm but that
takes a lot of Feltham don't worry I
don't think you'll be doing that today
but I do like I'm quite a firm filter
some people like things quite loose and
it's completely up to you and how you
feel it should be so here I am and I'm
just twisting and turning this all and
you keep moving it don't needle felt all
in one place because it'll only lock
together in that place and you'll end up
with a little hole first
so just twist and turn twist and turn
and keep going and you might need to
take your finger protector ZUP just to
feel what you think of it and you can
give it a switch so this is not too bad
it's getting there as you can see I'm
quite comfortable without my protectors
on but I do recommend you wear them if
you're starting and it just
a few times that it does hurt but it's
not the end of the world so just keep
twisting and turning and seeing what you
think about it and then give it a
squidge and it will become firm and you
will see I'll show you in a bit that the
hairs on the outside the wool on the
outside starts to the fluffy bits start
to disappear and you can also almost see
some of the needle marks where you've
been putting the needle in sounds a bit
odd but you'll know what I mean when you
see it this series I'm doing is needle
felting essentials and this is the
absolute beginner so here we go it's
getting a bit smaller and I'm just
showing you how far you don't have to
needle felt all the way through to the
other side as you put it in that is how
far it's going in naturally so you don't
have to go all the way through if you go
all the way through you've got more of a
chance of stabbing yourself so needle
felting essentials the videos that I'm
doing I'm doing this one for absolute
beginners and to show you you can
actually make something as an absolute
beginner the next one I'm going to do is
going through types of wool because
there's different types of all that I
didn't understand when I first started
oh yeah here we are I've just shown you
I've needle felted really firmly one
half of it and the other side I've left
looser and you can see that the fibers
are sticking out more on that side
[Music]
and that side that I've done really
quite well felted is a lot lot firmer
when you switch it so this is just to
show you that you are actually making a
difference the more you felt it so there
we go
I felt it it all round and then the last
thing always do with these boys is just
rub them in my hands like that
[Music]
and that just gives it a nice finish and
definitely makes it round so there you
go there's one bull do the others
it's the Thule and three or these
rainbow colors what you end up with
exactly so easy it's perfect and
fantastic what you do with these well
here we go you can put them as a
necklace you can make small ones as a
bracelet it could be a garland it could
be a mobile you could do the colors to
your own living room oh it's just so
many things you just thread a needle
through it and you can do it everyone
this is um to show you a whiteboard I
did this is really fluffy on the outside
so it hasn't been needle felted that
well and now another couple of minutes
later do you see all the fibers have
started to disappear on the outside and
it's a lot firmer give it a little
squidge so some of the other videos are
that I'm going to do it's going to
include the types of world types of
needles types of mats as well because
you will get through mats and it's
interesting to see what mats are out
there so next shape I'm just gonna whiz
through isn't is an oblong shape so I've
done a little white ball there that's a
really great base as a head for an
animal and this is a great base as a
body for an animal so I just roll it up
and then get the needle and then just
start knitting the end bits together so
it stays in and where your finger
protectors if you don't
comfortable without them just to show
you my needles
some of them come like this as a sort of
plane top and I always just put a bit of
tape around to make it easy the color
coding I'll talk about in the next video
[Music]
so take your oblong and just need a felt
it all the way through the middle when
you are dealing with the world you will
find bits of straw bits of hay
this is a natural product you know they
can't get everything else so just pull
it out because it will show if that's
the end piece of your product you don't
want any little bits showing just pull
them out they come out really easily so
I've just turned the end in a little bit
and in a minute I'm just going to turn
it up on its end and because I don't
like wearing the finger protectors what
you can do is hold it with another
needle same not gonna stab yourself and
that makes life a little bit easier so
just keep rolling it and then needle
felt either end and lo and behold you
will have an oblong shape when the
oblong shape is a really good base for
the body of any animal and I have got
several more videos I'll just show you
the animals in a minute what I've been
doing so there we go there's the oblong
base
and here's the base for my sheet and
this is another beginner project you
just need gray white and black world
that easy so here's the sheep in more
detail I show you how to do the face in
the eyes and the legs and here's
highland cow I do again very easy basic
beginner it's got a nice little top line
pretty cute so another thing you can do
beginner one ladybirds these could be
hair clips they can be brooches they
could just be as they are it's so easy
so simple to do and it's nice if you've
got a project but you can work them this
is something a little bit further along
the line it's got a wire frame you've
got clay horns and he's got actual herd
wig
well so he's lovely and then this is a
really firm felt I like to do horses
willful lot and try and get a nice mane
and tail female a feet
Moo's so there's so much you can do my
next video is going to be doing
Garland's of these do couple oak I hope
you've enjoyed this brief introduction
and subscribe and like for more videos
thanks for watching everybody